“Among the Whisperings and the Champagne and the Stars”: Echoes of Keats’ “Ode to a Nightingale” in The Great Gatsby When F. Scott Fitzgerald has Nick Carraway introduce Jay Gatsby in terms of his “romantic readiness such as I have never found in any other person” (2), one can interpret that statement in terms of medieval chivalry, Gatsby’s “gift for hope,” and Gatsby’s love for Daisy, but one can also explore Fitzgerald’s evocation of the British romantic poets and the way their influence enhances The Great Gatsby . Of the romantics, John Keats was clearly Fitzgerald’s favorite (McCall 521). His novel Tender Is the Night (1934) takes its title from a line in Keats’ “Ode to a Nightingale,” and The Great Gatsby frequently shares quotes and imagery with the poem. Keats’ treatment of time and the pastoral ideal in “Ode to a Nightingale” appears to have influenced Nick’s elegiac portrait of Gatsby as well as Gatsby’s romanticization of Daisy. Of course, it’s always possible that some of these parallels may be coincidental, and Fitzgerald usually disguised his influences. Still, tracing Fitzgerald’s adaptation of Keats’ imagery and poetic devices helps us understand how he converted British romanticism into an atmosphere of enchantment that heightens Gatsby and Daisy’s characterization, separating them from others in the novel as they share in a kind of Keatsian paradox: apprehending beauty in an existential world. To get a sense of how much Fitzgerald adored Keats’ poetry, one can turn to his letter to his daughter Frances of August 3, 1940 (written when she was approximately 19 years old): The Grecian Urn is unbearably beautiful, with every syllable as inevitable as the notes of Beethoven’s Ninth Symphony . . . . I suppose I’ve read it a hundred times. . . . Likewise with the Nightingale , which I can never read without tears in my eyes . . . and The Eve of Flannagan 2 St. Agnes , which has the richest, most sensuous imagery in English, not excepting Shakespeare. . . . In themselves, those . . . poems are a scale of workmanship for anybody who wants to know truly about words, their utter value for evocation, persuasion or charm. For awhile, after you quit Keats all other poetry seems to be only whistling or humming. ( The CrackUp 298) Moreover, critics have noted connections between Keats and Fitzgerald. Essays by George Monteiro and Joseph B. Wagner, both written for the Fitzgerald / Hemingway Annual, explore how Keats’ “The Eve of St. Agnes” and Endymion, respectively, have aspects that correspond to elements of The Great Gatsby . In “James Gatz and John Keats,” Monteiros mostly focuses on how a scene involving a “rich feast” of “cates and dainties” in “The Eve of St. Agnes” has several parallels to the passage in the novel where Daisy admires Gatsby’s shirts. Such opulent displays cause both Daisy and Madeline in the poem to weep with appreciation (293). Yet, while the Gatsbylike figure Porphyro succeeds in the “contest between love and time,” Gatsby ultimately fails in claiming Daisy the same way (294). In “ Gatsby and John Keats: Another Version,” Wagner explores how Gatsby is “an ironic version of the Endymion myth” where both Gatsby and Endymion “fall in love with inaccessible ideals” (912). Wagner most effectively examines the way both the poet and the American author use moon imagery. In Keats’ poem, the lover adores the “goddess of the moon,” and Fitzgerald includes a great deal of lunar imagery in The Great Gatsby (Wagner 92). Still, the romanticism of the novel has been corrupted by the greed and the materialism of American Dream, which makes any allusion to Endymion ironic by comparison. The most useful essay on the Keats/Gatsby correlations is Dan McCall’s “‘The SelfSame Song That Found a Path’: Keats and The Great Gatsby. ” In his study, McCall analyzes Keats’ sense of the “ambivalence of beauty” as it was shared by Fitzgerald, how the extremity of the poet’s appreciation of beauty would lead to contradictory reactions (522). In essence, extreme pleasure can become indistinguishable from something hurtful. As McCall puts it, “In the work of Keats the love of beauty Flannagan 3 becomes so intense, wrought to such a pitch, that it becomes almost indistinguishable from pain” (523). Both Keats and Fitzgerald also depict the difficulty of possessing beauty, how, as McCall writes, “to obtain beauty is to lose it” (528). Other tensions include how the complete fulfillment of beauty leads to death, and how the romantic persona maintains a nearreligious confusion between the eternal and the temporal as he tries to grasp beauty. McCall mostly examines these constrasting reactions in The Great Gatsby without considering the surrounding context of each scene in the novel. This essay will seek to better situate these contradictory romantic tensions within the novel’s deflating context of pragmatic, modern, and comparatively crude American culture. Ironically, the first major reference to Keats’ “Ode to a Nightingale” comes across as flippantly obvious, a bald attempt on Daisy’s part to paper over her husband’s transgression with his mistress Myrtle Wilson. When Nick has dinner with Jordan Baker, Daisy, and Tom at the Buchanan’s estate early in the novel, Myrtle keeps calling on the telephone, disrupting their leisurely evening. When Jordan tells Nick that “[Myrtle] might have the decency not to telephone him at dinner time. Don’t you think?”, Daisy returns to the dinner table and tries to mask the interruption with: “‘I looked outdoors for a minute, and it’s very romantic outdoors. There’s a bird on the lawn that I think must be a nightingale come over on the Cunard or White Star Line. He’s singing away’ Her voice sang: ‘It’s romantic, isn’t it, Tom’” (15)? By emphasizing how Daisy’s voice “sang,” Fitzgerald hints at a similarity between Daisy and the Nightingale that he will develop later as he keeps alluding to the seductive quality of Daisy’s voice. Both Daisy and the bird supply a means for Gatsby and the poem’s persona to escape time and enter a higher plane. Yet, here Daisy comes across as pitiful in her attempt to use literary allusions to reinstate a romantic atmosphere between her and her husband, one that has obviously been shattered by Myrtle’s machinations. Perhaps Fitzgerald included this reference to prepare the reader for the more pastoral world of Gatsby that Daisy will find as an attractive alternative to her marriage. Yet here, she haplessly tries to substitute a bird song for the loud mechanical ring of a telephone. The scene juxtaposes the 19th century Flannagan 4 pastoral romantic with the modern machine, just as later Gatsby will be repeatedly pulled away from his parties to talk business on the phone. Daisy’s reference to the two British shipping lines points to the immigrant nature of Keats’ imagery as it has to cross the Atlantic. The entire scene depicts how Daisy’s evocation of romance does not fit within the American crass, racist, pseudointellectual world of her husband Tom. When Nick turns his attention to Gatsby’s parties at the beginning of Chapter 3, one can sense how they provide a sense of Keatsian aesthetic of pleasure and escape: “There was music from my neighbor’s house through the summer nights. In his blue gardens men and girls came and went like moths among the whisperings and the champagne and the stars” (39). The syntax of “the whisperings and the champagne and the stars” makes them all equivalent elements of enchantment. The synesthesia found in Gatsby’s “orchestra playing yellow cocktail music” (40) has a parallel in “An Ode to a Nightingale” when the persona tries to “see” incense: “I cannot see what flowers are at my feet, / Nor what soft incense hangs upon the boughs” (412). It’s important that Gatsby’s parties and Midsummer Night’s Dream esque night scene imagery associated with the Nightingale are halflit, starry, and pastoral. Gatsby intends for these parties to lure Daisy across the Long Island Sound, and he doesn’t mind waiting for years for her arrival because of the timeless element in his idea of their former romance in Louisville. When Jordan tells Nick later of Gatsby’s plan to meet Daisy at Nick’s bungalow, Nick wonders “[Gatsby] had waited five years and bought a mansion where he dispensed starlight to casual moths” (78). He needs Daisy to complete the enchantment just as the nightingale provides an escape for the persona in Keats’ poem. The ability to transform one’s relationship to time is a big part of this romantic striving on Gatsby’s part. He means to cancel the intervening five years (when Daisy married and had a child), and act as if it never happened, as if he could reclaim a love that transcended any such temporal concerns. When Gatsby tells Nick of his plan, Nick sensibly replies that “You can’t repeat the past.” Gatsby’s response summarizes both the glamour and the tomfoolery of his romantic stance: “‘Can’t repeat the Flannagan 5 past?” he cried incredulously. ‘Why of course you can’” (110)! In Keats’ “Ode to a Nightingale,” the Nightingale’s song and position in the night trees promises a similar timeless realm away from the human concerns of age, the ravages of time (“The weariness, the fever, and the fret / Here, where men sit and hear each other groan” (234)). Fitzgerald draws another exact correlation to the nightingale and Daisy near the end of Chapter 5 when he alludes to the poem’s line “here there is no light, / Save what from heaven is with breezes blown / Through verdurous glooms and winding mossy ways” (3840). As McCall points out, “Fitzgerald quite consciously draws upon Keats’ language” (521) when he has Gatsby sit down with Daisy after showing her his largely empty mansion soon after their five year reunion: “He lit Daisy’s cigarette from a trembling match, and sat down with her on a couch far across the room, where there was no light save what the gleaming floor bounced in from the hall” (94). Now united with the dream woman of his youth, Gatsby has arrived at the “embalmed darkness” (43) of Keats’ Ode, but as in the case of Daisy pitifully trying to evoke a romantic moment with Tom earlier, Fitzgerald lightly mocks Gatsby’s transcendent moment by including Klipspringer’s ludicrous crude playing of “Ain’t we got fun” on the piano in the same scene. Once again, Fitzgerald includes a note of modern disillusionment to a previously romanticized scene. As the song lyrics point out, “ One thing’s sure and nothing’s surer / The rich get richer and the poor getchildren ” (95). The reference to the “rich” evokes Tom and the way he will soon puncture the enchantment of Gatsby’s next party with his rude condescending reactions. Despite Daisy’s obvious wealth, the reference to children may perhaps be associated with Daisy’s little girl Pammy who Gatsby has such difficulty believing in the existence of when he sees her in the novel (117). Just as Keats liked to combine opposities in the midst of aesthetic rapture, the way pleasure can so easily evoke pain, and extreme bliss can so quickly lead to death, so does Fitzgerald like to juxtapose an atmosphere of Keatsian enchantment with the more industrial automated bleak world of conspicuous consumption, jarring sounds of the telephone, tinny 1920s pop songs, and the judgments of Tom finding Flannagan 6 fault with the nouveau riche . As much as Gatsby and Daisy strive for a higher beauty, circumstances of the novel keeps puncturing their attempts to transcend their domestic dramas and attain some timeless sphere. Just as the persona of “Ode to a Nightingale” keeps trying and failing to escape the vicissitudes of “leadeneyed despairs” (28), so do Gatsby and to a lesser extent Daisy attain a brief, unsatisfactory return to their former love in Louisville five years before the main events of the novel. No wonder Keats’ poem has so many mood swings, nor is it any surprise that Nick becomes so disillusioned with the East. Gatsby repeatedly reaches for the green light, but his striving for romantic happiness carries within its own negation. In their respective works of literature, Keats and Fitzgerald both still appear to prefer the attempt at bliss, the sense of quickening that comes from hope or “romantic readiness,” to the relative dreariness of not trying at all.